Guide to the Black Trade Unionists Leadership Committee Records and Photographs WAG.138
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Black Trade Unionists Leadership Committee Records and Photographs
1968-1987
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Black Trade Unionists Leadership Committee
Scotland, Thomas
WAG.138
2 Linear Feet in 2 record cartons and 1 manuscript box.
The Black Trade Unionists Leadership Committee grew out of a loose coalition of New York City African-American trade-unionists, formed during the 1968 teachers' strike. In 1971 it became a committee of the New York City Central Labor Council, concerned with African-American affairs. The collection contains minutes, correspondence, subject files, and photographs.
Custodial History
These papers were collected by Austin Ottley during his tenure as Secretary of the BTULC. They were donated to the Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives by Thomas Scotland, president of the BTULC, in December 1996.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
The Black Trade Unionists Leadership Committee grew out of the city-wide strike by the United Federation of Teachers in 1968. The dispute arose out of a school decentralization plan that gave communities more control over schools. The Community School Board of Ocean-Hill Brownsville, a school district in Brooklyn, allegedly violated a key section of the UFT's contract by transferring nine teachers out of the district. The long strike put the district in a state of turmoil, with passions running high in the community and among union members.
In 1968 A. Philip Randolph brought together black trade-unionists in an attempt to develop support for the teachers' union. The group decided to meet intermittently to discuss issues of mutual concern and to seek solutions that would benefit black workers both in and out of the labor movement. At its inception the group worked as an ad hoc committee and had no permanent officers. One of its first efforts was to develop a "big brother" program, whereby trade-unionists counseled young workers who had no previous employment experience.
The committee was formally organized in 1971 as the Black Trade Unionists Committee of the New York City Central Labor Council. Its first president was John Burnell of the Transport Workers Union. Toward the end of 1973 it changed its name to the Black Trade Unionists Leadership Committee. The group's objectives were to foster good relations between the black community and the labor movement, to increase the political involvement of black trade unionists - both in the field of civil rights in general and to advance the interests of black workers specifically, and to advance the goals of the NYC Central Labor Council.
The Committee makes use of educational conferences, voter registration drives, community service projects, and scholarship awards to advance its program. Its educational conferences and awards dinner-dances became annual events beginning in the early 1970s.
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains minutes, correspondence, subject files, and photographs. Minutes (incomplete) are of Executive Board and General Membership meetings. Correspondence includes both officers' outgoing correspondence and incoming correspondence from a number of labor, civil rights and community organizations. Also included in the collection are financial reports, records of conferences and dinner dances, press releases and other publicity material, and seven files of material documenting BTULC Secretary Austin Ottley's work as a student at Empire State College's Labor Division, where his mentor was Dr. Harry Kelber. Photographs are from the 1970s through mid-1980s and depict a variety of events, meetings, speakers, headshots, and group portraits.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged chronologically in Series I-III and Series IV and V are arranged alphabetically.
The files are grouped into 5 series:
Missing Title
I: Constitution and By-Laws
II: Minutes
III: Correspondence
IV: General Files
V: Photographs
Related Archival Materials
United Federation of Teachers Records WAG.022
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Thomas Scotland, president of the Black Trade Unionists Leadership Committee, in 1996. The accession numbers associated with this gift are 1996.001 and 1996.007.
Labor movement |z New York (State) |z New York.; Photographs.; Labor unions -- United States.; African American labor union members.; Labor union members.; Correspondence.; Minutes (administrative records); United Federation of Teachers; Coalition of Black Trade Unionists (U.S.); AFL-CIO. New York City Central Labor Council. Black Trade Unionists Leadership Committee; AFL-CIO. New York City Central Labor Council; Burnell, John .; Ottley, Austin.; Scotland, Thomas
- Series I: Constitution and By-Laws
  - Constitution and By-Laws, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Series II: Minutes, 1973-1985
  - Minutes: Executive Board and General Meetings, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Minutes: Executive Board and General Meetings, 1976, 1980-1985 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Series III: Correspondence, 1969-1986
  - Correspondence, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Series IV: General Files, 1968-1987
  - Activities Reports, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - AFL-CIO News Conference, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - August Martin H.S., 1972 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Brennan, Peter: Support, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - BTULC: General, undated, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - BTULC: General, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - BTULC: Newsletters, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Bus Outing, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Certificates: Cornell ILR, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - CETA Grants, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - CETA Grants, 1980-1982 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Clippings; Articles, undated, 1973, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Clippings; Articles, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Coalition of Black Trade Unionists, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Conference on Crime Prevention, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Communications Workers of America, Local 1187, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Dinner Dance, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Dinner Dance, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Dinner Dance, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Dinner Dance, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Dinner Dance, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Dinner Dance, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Dinner Dance, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Dinner Dance, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Dinner Dance, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Educational Conference, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Finances, 1972-1974 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Finances, 1979-1984 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Human Resources Development Institute, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers: Minority Caucus, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Kelber, Harry: Endowment, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Labor Chronicle(Burnell, John), 1974 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Membership Applications, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - NAACP, 1982-1984 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - New York City Central Labor Council: Civil Rights Conference, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - New York City Central Labor Council: Civil Rights Conference, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - New York City Residential Manpower Center, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - New York State Black and Puerto Rican Legislative Caucus, undated, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Ottley, Austin: American Foreign Policy, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Ottley, Austin: Arbitration, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Ottley, Austin: Course Work Misc., 1972 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Ottley, Austin: Effective Communication, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Ottley, Austin: Reports, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Ottley, Austin: Seminar for Union Organizers, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Ottley, Austin: Sociology of Work, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Owens, Major, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Picnic, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Political Action, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Program, 1982-1984 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Randolph, A. Philip, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Registration Forms (Political), 1982-1985 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Romney, Ed, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Scholarships, 1980-1985 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Spanish Course, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Steering Committee for Negro Labor Leaders, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Summer Conference (Cornell), 1972 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Summer Conference: 2nd, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Summer Conference: 3rd, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Summer Conference: 4th, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Summer Conference: 5th, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Summer Conference: 7th, 1975-1978 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Series V: Photographs, 1968-1986, circa 1968-1986
  - Camp Radalbek, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Contact Sheets, Event, circa 1970-1980 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Contact Sheets, Event, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Contact Sheets, Event, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Contact Sheets, Event (1 Print), undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Demonstration Meeting, circa 1970-1979 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Dinner Dance, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Dinner Dance, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Event, circa 1968-1974 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Event, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Events, circa 1970-1986 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Events, circa 1978-1985 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Events and Headshots, circa 1970-1980 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Events and Speakers, 1976-1978 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Group Photos, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Headshots, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Headshots - Edgar Romney, Olga Diaz, Edward Cleary, undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Meeting, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Miscellaneous Photographs, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Miscellaneous Photographs, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Miscellaneous Photographs, undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Portraits by Sam Reiss, undated (Box 3, Folder 22)